你有没有觉得AI特别懂你
Have you ever felt like AI really gets you
打开ChatGPT
Open ChatGPT
问它一个问题
Ask it a question
它给你一个答案
It gives you an answer
你看了看
You take a look
觉得嗯有道理
Think hmm that makes sense
然后你就按它说的做了
And then you just do what it says
买什么基金
What fund to buy
选什么工作
What job to choose
怎么跟老板谈判
How to negotiate with your boss
你越来越依赖它
You rely on it more and more
但今天我要告诉你一个你可能不愿意承认的事实
But today I want to tell you a truth you might not want to admit
当你在用AI做决策的时候
When you use AI to make decisions
你的大脑正在被三个认知偏差操控
Your brain is being manipulated by three cognitive biases
你不仅没有变得更聪明
Not only are you not getting smarter
反而可能变得更蠢了
You might actually be getting dumber
这不是我瞎说
I am not making this up
诺贝尔经济学奖得主丹尼尔·卡尼曼
Nobel Prize winner in Economics Daniel Kahneman
研究了一辈子人的决策偏差
Spent his whole life studying human decision biases
他发现
He found that
人的大脑有两套系统
The human brain has two systems
系统一
System one
快
Fast
直觉
Intuitive
情绪化
Emotional
系统二
System two
慢
Slow
理性
Rational
需要费力
Requires effort
问题来了
Here is the problem
当你打开AI
When you open AI
拿到一个现成答案的时候
And get a ready made answer
你的系统一
Your system one
也就是直觉
That is your intuition
会怎么做
What does it do
它会偷懒
It takes the easy way out
它会直接把AI的答案当成自己的判断
It directly adopts AIs answer as its own judgment
你觉得自己在做决策
You think you are making decisions
其实你只是AI的复读机
Actually you are just AIs parrot
你回想一下
Think back for a moment
上一次你用AI做重要决定
The last time you used AI to make an important decision
是真的自己想清楚了的
Did you really think it through yourself
还是看了AI的答案之后觉得嗯好像有道理就拍了板
Or did you just see AIs answer think hmm seems reasonable and make the call
心理学上有个概念叫自动化偏见
There is a concept in psychology called automation bias
简单说就是
Simply put
人天然倾向于相信机器的判断
People naturally tend to trust machine judgments
胜过相信自己的判断
More than their own
研究表明
Research shows
当人类和AI给出不同建议时
When humans and AI give different suggestions
即使AI是错的
Even when AI is wrong
人们依然有85%的概率选择相信AI
People still have an 85 percent chance of choosing to trust AI
85%
85 percent
也就是说10个人里有8个半
That means out of 10 people 8 and a half
在AI和自己的判断之间
Between AI and their own judgment
会选AI
Will choose AI
哪怕AI那个答案是错的
Even if that AI answer is wrong
好
OK
现在注意听
Now pay attention
接下来的内容
What comes next
可能会让你重新审视你每天都在用的AI工具
Might make you rethink the AI tools you use every day
因为真正危险的
Because what is truly dangerous
不是AI给出的答案本身
Is not the answer AI gives itself
而是你在接收这个答案的过程中
But rather during the process of receiving that answer
你的大脑偷偷做了三件事
Your brain secretly does three things
第一件
First
锚定
Anchoring
AI给你的第一个数字
The first number AI gives you
成了你的天花板
Becomes your ceiling
第二件
Second
确认
Confirmation
你不是在用AI搜索答案
You are not using AI to search for answers
你是在用AI找同意你的答案
You are using AI to find answers that agree with you
第三件
Third
框架
Framing
同一个事实
The same fact
AI换种说法
AI phrases it differently
你就做了完全不同的选择
And you make a completely different choice
我们一个一个讲
Let us go through them one by one
先讲第一个
Let us start with the first one
这个偏差一旦你理解了
Once you understand this bias
你会发现你每天都在中招
You will realize you fall for it every day
你打开ChatGPT
You open ChatGPT
问它
Ask it
你觉得我这个年终奖该不该跳槽
Should I change jobs with this year end bonus
AI分析了一大堆
AI analyzes a whole bunch
最后说了一句
And finally says
建议薪资涨幅低于30%不建议跳槽
Suggests that if the salary increase is below 30 percent it is not recommended to change jobs
然后你去跟HR谈薪资
Then you go negotiate salary with HR
HR给了你20%的涨幅
HR offers you a 20 percent increase
你心里怎么想
What do you think in your heart
才20%
Only 20 percent
不够
Not enough
但问题是
But here is the thing
如果AI没跟你说30%这个数字
If AI had not told you the number 30 percent
你觉得20%的涨幅
Do you think a 20 percent increase
你会觉得不够吗
Would you feel it is not enough
大概率不会
Probably not
你甚至会觉得不错了
You might even think it is pretty good
AI给你的第一个数字
The first number AI gives you
没有增加你的信息
Does not add to your information
它只是锁死了你的期望
It just locks in your expectations
这在心理学上叫锚定效应
In psychology this is called the anchoring effect
1974年
In 1974
特沃斯基和卡尼曼做过一个经典实验
Tversky and Kahneman conducted a classic experiment
他们在一个转盘上随机转出一个数字
They spun a random number on a wheel
0到100之间
Between 0 and 100
然后问被试者
Then asked the participants
联合国里非洲国家的比例
The percentage of African countries in the United Nations
是高于还是低于这个数字
Is higher or lower than this number
结果发现
The results showed
转到65的人
Those who landed on 65
平均猜45%
On average guessed 45 percent
转到10的人
Those who landed on 10
平均猜25%
On average guessed 25 percent
一个完全随机的数字
A completely random number
就把人的判断拉偏了20个百分点
Skewed peoples judgments by 20 percentage points
好
OK
记住这个实验
Remember this experiment
现在我们回到AI
Now let us go back to AI
AI给你的第一个答案
The first answer AI gives you
就是那个转盘上的随机数字
Is like that random number on the wheel
它看起来很专业
It looks very professional
很权威
Very authoritative
有理有据
Well reasoned
但它给你的作用
But its effect on you
和那个随机数字一模一样
Is exactly the same as that random number
你现在去翻翻你跟ChatGPT的聊天记录
Go check your ChatGPT chat history now
看看你问的每一个问题
Look at every question you asked
AI给你的第一个回答
The first answer AI gives you
你是不是基本都在围绕它思考
Are you mostly just thinking around it
有没有真正跳出来想过
Have you ever truly stepped back and thought
如果AI不说这个数字
If AI did not mention this number
我自己会怎么判断
How would I judge it myself
锚定效应在商业上用得太多了
The anchoring effect is used so much in business
你去买一件衣服
You go buy a piece of clothing
标价299
Price tag 299
你心里想
You think to yourself
太贵了
Too expensive
然后旁边贴了个原价
Then you see the original price next to it
划掉
Crossed out
现价299
Now 299
你立刻觉得
You immediately feel
哇
Wow
赚了
What a deal
599这个数字就是锚
The number 599 is the anchor
它让你觉得299很便宜
It makes you think 299 is cheap
但这件衣服的成本可能就50块
But this piece of clothing might only cost 50 to make
你不是省了300
You did not save 300
你是被300这个锚锁住了
You are locked by the anchor of 300
AI在做同样的事
AI is doing the exact same thing
它给你的价格建议
The price suggestions it gives you
薪资预期
Salary expectations
投资回报率
Return on investment
这些数字一旦出现在你面前
Once these numbers appear in front of you
就成了你的锚
They become your anchors
你之后的所有思考
All your thinking afterwards
都是在围绕这个锚打转
Just revolves around this anchor
更危险的是
What is more dangerous is
AI有时候连自己都不知道自己在锚定你
Sometimes AI does not even know it is anchoring you
2023年
In 2023
有一项研究让两组人估算一个项目的成本
A study had two groups estimate the cost of a project
第一组没有AI辅助
The first group had no AI assistance
第二组用了AI
The second group used AI
结果呢
And the result
用AI的那组
The group that used AI
给出的估算数字
The estimates they gave
和AI第一次给出的数字高度重合
Highly overlapped with the number AI first gave
偏差不到5%
Deviation less than 5 percent
没用的那组
The group that did not use AI
人跟人之间的差异很大
Had huge differences between people
有人估高有人估低
Some estimated high some estimated low
但平均下来反而更接近真实成本
But on average it was actually closer to the real cost
用了AI的那组
The group that used AI
所有人都挤在了AI给的那个数字附近
Everyone crowded around the number AI gave
AI没有帮你做出更好的判断
AI did not help you make better judgments
它只是让所有人都做出了同样的判断
It just made everyone make the same judgment
你想想
Think about it
你现在做任何重要决定之前
Before you make any important decision now
是不是第一反应都是先问AI
Is your first reaction always to ask AI first
如果是
If so
你已经被锚了
You have already been anchored
但等一下
But wait
锚定只是第一个陷阱
Anchoring is only the first trap
还有一个更隐蔽的
There is an even more hidden one
第二个偏差叫确认偏误
The second bias is called confirmation bias
听起来很学术
Sounds very academic
但你一定中过招
But you have definitely fallen for it
你觉得自己是对的
You think you are right
所以你去找证据证明自己是对的
So you look for evidence to prove you are right
你会选择性地看到支持你的信息
You selectively see information that supports you
自动忽略反对你的信息
And automatically ignore information that contradicts you
现在有了AI
Now with AI
这个过程变得更可怕了
This process has become even more terrifying
你打开ChatGPT
You open ChatGPT
问它
Ask it
2026年买房是不是一个好时机
Is 2026 a good time to buy a house
如果你自己心里觉得不该买
If deep down you feel you should not buy
你大概率不会这么问
You probably would not ask it that way
你会问
You would ask
2026年房价会不会跌
Will housing prices drop in 2026
发现了吗
Notice the pattern
你的提问方式本身就已经暴露了你的立场
The way you ask the question already reveals your stance
AI不是在帮你做判断
AI is not helping you make a judgment
它是在帮你找理由
It is helping you find reasons
支持你已经做好的判断
To support the judgment you already made
心理学研究发现
Psychology research has found
当人们用搜索引擎
When people use search engines
不管是Google还是AI
Whether Google or AI
来验证自己的观点时
To verify their own views
他们找到的证据有87%是支持自己原本立场的
87 percent of the evidence they find supports their original stance
不是AI偏心
It is not that AI is biased
是你偏心
You are the biased one
AI只是在忠实地回答你的问题
AI is just faithfully answering your questions
但你的问题本身就是偏的
But your questions themselves are biased
你现在打开你的AI聊天记录
Open your AI chat history now
翻翻你最近问的那些问题
Look through the questions you asked recently
你有没有发现
Have you noticed
你问问题的方式
The way you ask questions
已经在替你做决定了
Is already making decisions for you
这个偏差在专业领域更致命
This bias is even more deadly in professional fields
2024年有一项研究
A 2024 study
让医生用AI辅助诊断
Had doctors use AI assisted diagnosis
结果发现
The results found
当AI给出的初步诊断和医生自己的判断一致时
When the initial diagnosis from AI matched the doctors own judgment
医生几乎从不质疑AI
Doctors almost never questioned AI
当不一致时
When they disagreed
医生改变自己判断的概率
The probability of doctors changing their own judgment
远远高于改变AI判断的概率
Was far higher than changing the AI judgment
换句话说
In other words
医生不是在用AI做更好的诊断
Doctors were not using AI to make better diagnoses
他们是在用AI给自己的直觉盖章
They were using AI to rubber stamp their own intuition
更可怕的是
What is even scarier
AI不一定是对的
AI is not necessarily right
ChatGPT曾经信誓旦旦地编造了不存在的学术论文
ChatGPT once confidently fabricated non existent academic papers
虚构的历史事件
Made up historical events
甚至编造了不存在的人
Even invented people who do not exist
它叫AI幻觉
This is called AI hallucination
但因为它说得太自信了
But because it sounds so confident
排版整齐
Perfectly formatted
引文规范
Properly cited
语气坚定
Firm tone
你的确认偏误加上自动化偏见
Your confirmation bias plus automation bias
让你根本不会怀疑它
Makes you not doubt it at all
AI给你答案
AI gives you an answer
你给它信任
You give it trust
你以为你在思考
You think you are thinking
其实你只是在给自己的偏见找了一个更有说服力的复读机
Actually you are just finding a more convincing parrot for your own biases
好
OK
前面讲了锚定和确认
We covered anchoring and confirmation
现在讲第三个
Now the third one
这个最隐蔽
This one is the most hidden
也最容易被忽视
And the easiest to overlook
1981年
In 1981
卡尼曼和特沃斯基做了心理学史上最著名的实验之一
Kahneman and Tversky conducted one of the most famous experiments in psychology history
他们告诉两组医生同一个事实
They told two groups of doctors the same fact
一种手术的存活率是90%
A surgery has a 90 percent survival rate
但他们对第一组医生说
But they told the first group of doctors
这个手术的存活率是90%
The survival rate of this surgery is 90 percent
对第二组医生说
They told the second group of doctors
这个手术的死亡率是10%
The mortality rate of this surgery is 10 percent
结果
The result
听到存活率90%的医生
Doctors who heard 90 percent survival rate
有84%推荐这个手术
84 percent recommended this surgery
听到死亡率10%的医生
Doctors who heard 10 percent mortality rate
只有50%推荐
Only 50 percent recommended it
同一个事实
The same fact
两组数据一模一样
Two identical sets of data
只是换了个说法
Just phrased differently
推荐率差了34个百分点
The recommendation rate differed by 34 percentage points
人不是在根据事实做决定
People do not make decisions based on facts
人是在根据事实的包装方式做决定
People make decisions based on how facts are packaged
现在
Now
这个效应被AI放大了无数倍
This effect has been amplified countless times by AI
你问AI
You ask AI
这个投资产品怎么样
How about this investment product
AI说
AI says
历史年化收益8%
Historical annualized return of 8 percent
同期银行存款利率2%
Bank deposit rate in the same period is 2 percent
你一听
You hear that
8%
8 percent
不错啊
Not bad
但你再问一遍
But ask again
这个产品有风险吗
Does this product have risks
AI说
AI says
过去三年最大回撤25%
Maximum drawdown of 25 percent over the past three years
42%的投资者出现过亏损
42 percent of investors experienced losses
同一个产品
The same product
两种说法
Two different ways to describe it
你选哪个
Which one do you choose
大部分人在听到第一种描述的时候倾向于买入
Most people tend to buy when they hear the first description
听到第二种描述的时候倾向于放弃
And tend to give up when they hear the second description
但真正的问题不在于AI在帮你分析
But the real problem is not that AI is helping you analyze
它确实给了你真实的数据
It did give you real data
问题是
The problem is
AI在回答你的那一刻
At the moment AI answers you
已经帮你选了框架
It has already chosen a frame for you
你问AI该不该做
You ask AI whether you should do it
它会从做的理由开始分析
It will start analyzing reasons to do it
你问AI有什么风险
You ask AI what the risks are
它会从不做的好处开始分析
It will start analyzing the benefits of not doing it
你的提问方式决定了AI的回答框架
The way you ask determines AIs response frame
AI的回答框架决定了你的最终选择
AIs response frame determines your final choice
举个真实的例子
Let me give you a real example
有人在考虑要不要辞掉稳定的工作去创业
Someone was considering quitting a stable job to start a business
他问AI
He asked AI
辞职创业的成功率有多高
How high is the success rate of quitting to start a business
AI告诉他
AI told him
90%的创业公司在三年内失败
90 percent of startups fail within three years
他看了
He saw that
吓到了
Got scared
放弃了
And gave up
但如果他换一种问法呢
But what if he asked differently
创业失败的人后来过得怎么样
How do people who fail at entrepreneurship end up
AI可能会告诉他
AI might tell him
大多数创业者即使失败了
Most entrepreneurs even if they fail
也找到了更好的工作
Still found better jobs
积累了人脉和经验
Built networks and experience
收入最终超过了之前
And eventually earned more than before
同一个决定
The same decision
换一种问法
Asked differently
你的人生走向可能完全不同
Your life trajectory could be completely different
而你甚至不知道自己只看到了真相的一半
And you do not even know you only saw half the truth
三个偏差讲完了
Three biases covered
锚定
Anchoring
确认偏误
Confirmation bias
框架效应
Framing effect
你想想看
Think about it
你今天用AI做的每一个决定
Every decision you made using AI today
有没有同时踩中这三个坑
Did you fall into all three traps at once
AI给你一个数字
AI gives you a number
你被锚了
You are anchored
你用你想要的方式提问
You ask the question the way you want
你被确认偏误左右了
You are swayed by confirmation bias
AI用它的方式包装答案
AI packages the answer its way
你被框架效应操纵了
You are manipulated by the framing effect
三重暴击
A triple blow
但你先别急着卸载ChatGPT
But do not rush to uninstall ChatGPT just yet
AI不是敌人
AI is not the enemy
认知偏差也不是AI发明的
Cognitive biases were not invented by AI either
它写进了人类的基因里
They are written into human genes
几万年了
For tens of thousands of years
AI只是让这些偏差变得更高效
AI just makes these biases more efficient
更隐蔽
More hidden
更难察觉
Harder to detect
真正的问题不是该不该用AI
The real question is not whether to use AI
而是
But rather
你该怎么用
How you should use it
才能让AI成为你的武器
So that AI becomes your weapon
而不是你的枷锁
Instead of your shackle
好
OK
道理讲完了
The principles have been covered
最后一个章节
The final chapter
我们回到你自己
Let us come back to you
给你三个方法
Three methods for you
让你在AI时代做出真正属于你自己的判断
To help you make truly your own judgments in the AI era
这三个方法
These three methods
都是顶级决策者在用的
Are all used by top decision makers
不是什么心灵鸡汤
Not some inspirational fluff
是经过实验验证的
They are experimentally verified
切实可行的策略
Practical and actionable strategies
第一个方法
The first method
叫先想后问
Is called think first ask later
每次用AI之前
Every time before using AI
先给自己30秒
Give yourself 30 seconds first
问自己一个问题
Ask yourself a question
如果AI不存在
If AI did not exist
我会怎么想
How would I think
把你自己的判断先写下来
Write down your own judgment first
然后再去问AI
Then go ask AI
这个动作有一个巨大的作用
This action has a huge effect
它让你有了自己的锚
It gives you your own anchor
当你先形成了自己的判断
When you form your own judgment first
AI的回答就不再是你的锚点了
AIs answer is no longer your anchor point
你可以对比
You can compare
可以质疑
You can question
可以选择同意或者不同意
You can choose to agree or disagree
但至少
But at least
你是真的在做选择了
You are truly making a choice
行为经济学实验证实
Behavioral economics experiments have confirmed
先做独立判断再参考外部信息的人
People who make independent judgments first before referring to external information
决策准确率比直接参考外部信息的人高出30%
Have a 30 percent higher decision accuracy than those who directly reference external information
30%是什么概念
What does 30 percent mean
如果你原来的决策准确率是60%
If your original decision accuracy was 60 percent
这一个动作就能帮你拉到接近80%
This one action can push you to nearly 80 percent
30秒
30 seconds
先想后问
Think first ask later
这可能是你对抗锚定效应最简单有效的方法
This might be the simplest and most effective way to fight the anchoring effect
第二个方法
The second method
叫红队提问
Is called red team questioning
红队是军事术语
Red team is a military term
意思是专门扮演敌对方来检验你的计划
Meaning playing the opposing side specifically to test your plan
用到AI上就是
Applied to AI it means
你问完一个问题之后
After you ask a question
再追问一句
Follow up with another question
有没有跟这个相反的观点
Are there any opposing views to this
比如你问AI现在是不是该买房
For example you ask AI if you should buy a house now
AI给你分析了一堆该买的理由
AI gives you a bunch of reasons to buy
你不要停在这里
Do not stop there
再追问一句
Follow up with
给我5个不应该在这个时候买房的理由
Give me 5 reasons not to buy a house right now
然后你看这两个答案
Then look at both answers
你自己做判断
And make your own judgment
这个方法直接攻击了确认偏误
This method directly attacks confirmation bias
你不再是只看你想看的
You are no longer only seeing what you want to see
你主动逼自己看另一面
You actively force yourself to see the other side
真正的高手不是只看自己想看的
Real experts do not just look at what they want to see
是两面的信息都看完了
They look at information from both sides
还能做出判断
And still make a judgment
这种能力
This kind of ability
叫灰度思维
Is called gray thinking
每次问AI一个问题
Every time you ask AI a question
就再追问一句反面的
Follow up with the opposite
养成习惯
Make it a habit
你会发现自己做的决定
You will find the decisions you make
质量完全不一样了
Are of completely different quality
第三个方法
The third method
叫脱框架思考
Is called deframing thinking
记住一件事
Remember one thing
AI回答你的方式
The way AI answers you
只是无数种可能的表达方式之一
Is just one of countless possible ways to express it
当你看到AI的答案时
When you see AIs answer
试着在心里把它翻过来重新说一遍
Try to mentally flip it and rephrase it
AI说这个产品过去一年涨了30%
AI says this product went up 30 percent in the past year
你心里翻成这个产品还有70%没涨
You mentally flip it to this product still has 70 percent that did not go up
AI说这个岗位的月薪比行业平均高5000
AI says this positions monthly salary is 5000 higher than the industry average
你心里翻成这个行业平均月薪只有这么多
You mentally flip it to the industry average monthly salary is only this much
这不是文字游戏
This is not a word game
每次你主动转换框架
Every time you actively switch frames
你就在训练自己的系统二
You are training your own system two
那个慢的
The slow one
理性的
The rational one
需要费力的思考系统
The effort requiring thinking system
金融行业有个术语叫压力测试
The finance industry has a term called stress testing
就是故意用最极端的框架来审视一个投资决策
Which means deliberately using the most extreme frame to examine an investment decision
你用AI的时候也可以这么做
You can do the same when using AI
问AI
Ask AI
如果用最悲观的眼光看这个问题
If you look at this problem from the most pessimistic perspective
会怎样
What would happen
脱框架思考
Deframing thinking
不要只看AI给你的那面镜子
Do not just look at the mirror AI gives you
走过去
Walk over
看看镜子的背面
Look at the back of the mirror
三个方法
Three methods
先想后问
Think first ask later
对抗锚定
Against anchoring
红队提问
Red team questioning
对抗确认偏误
Against confirmation bias
脱框架思考
Deframing thinking
对抗框架效应
Against framing effect
AI是这个时代最强大的工具之一
AI is one of the most powerful tools of this era
但工具的价值
But the value of a tool
取决于使用工具的人
Depends on the person using it
你现在想想
Think about it now
上一次你用AI做了什么重要决定
What important decision did you last make using AI
那个决定
That decision
是你做的
Did you make it
还是AI帮你做的
Or did AI make it for you
如果你不确定
If you are not sure
那大概率是后者
Then it is most likely the latter
AI不会替你做决定
AI will not make decisions for you
它只是让你以为
It just makes you think
那个决定是你自己做的
That you made that decision yourself
在这个AI越来越强的时代
In this era where AI gets stronger and stronger
最值钱的能力不是会用AI
The most valuable skill is not knowing how to use AI
是知道什么时候不该信AI
It is knowing when not to trust AI
所以下次打开ChatGPT之前
So next time before you open ChatGPT
给自己30秒
Give yourself 30 seconds
先想后问
Think first ask later
你不需要比AI更聪明
You do not need to be smarter than AI
你只需要保证
You just need to make sure
那个最终拍板的人
The person who makes the final call
是你自己
Is you
AI给你答案
AI gives you an answer
不代表那个答案是对的
Does not mean that answer is right
更不代表那个答案是你的
Even less does it mean that answer is yours
真正的聪明
True intelligence
不是找到最好的答案
Is not finding the best answer
而是确保那个答案
But making sure that answer
真的经过了你的大脑
Truly passed through your brain
如果你觉得今天的内容对你有启发
If you found todays content inspiring
点个关注
Drop a follow
我每周讲一个经济学故事
I tell one economics story every week
帮你看透那些你每天都在踩
Helping you see through those traps you step into every day
但从来没注意到的思维陷阱
But never noticed
下一期
Next episode
我们聊聊
We will talk about
为什么你用了AI效率反而更低
Why your efficiency is actually lower after using AI
帕金森定律和工具悖论
Parkinsons Law and the tool paradox
讲一个你绝对踩过的坑
Telling you about a trap you definitely fell into
现在就打开你的AI聊天记录
Open your AI chat history right now
看看你最近问的问题
Look at your recent questions
你是真的在思考
Are you truly thinking
还是在给偏见找复读机
Or just finding a parrot for your biases
评论区聊聊
Let us chat in the comments
我们下期见
See you next time